<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Max Rosett</title><link href="http://writing.maxrosett.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://writing.maxrosett.com/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://writing.maxrosett.com/</id><updated>2020-03-01T12:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>What I Learned From a Year of Directed Reading</title><link href="http://writing.maxrosett.com/what-i-learned-from-a-year-of-directed-reading.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-03-01T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-03-01T12:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Max Rosett</name></author><id>tag:writing.maxrosett.com,2020-03-01:/what-i-learned-from-a-year-of-directed-reading.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last year, I wrote a piece called &lt;a href="http://writing.maxrosett.com/thirty-books-before-thirty.html"&gt;“Thirty Books I Want to Read Before I Turn Thirty.”&lt;/a&gt; The somewhat eclectic list actually consisted of twenty-four books, with empty slots left to add six more as the year went on. Roughly two-thirds of the books were well-known classics, while the remainder …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last year, I wrote a piece called &lt;a href="http://writing.maxrosett.com/thirty-books-before-thirty.html"&gt;“Thirty Books I Want to Read Before I Turn Thirty.”&lt;/a&gt; The somewhat eclectic list actually consisted of twenty-four books, with empty slots left to add six more as the year went on. Roughly two-thirds of the books were well-known classics, while the remainder were contemporary fiction or non-fiction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although I’ve always read articles and the like voraciously, I neglected books until recently, and my knowledge of the “great books” was nearly nonexistent.  The goal of this project was to remedy that. As I wrote last year, “Online articles can be a decent substitute for books on non-fiction topics of immediate interest, but only rarely do they touch on the human condition in a deep way… As I look at gaps in my own knowledge and thinking, I appreciate the value of deliberate undertakings.” &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project succeeded, although I still have much more reading to do. Here are some of the lessons I learned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Literature changes and improves as you get older.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;The Odyssey&lt;/em&gt; has far more layers than I noticed in eighth grade. I always imagined literature as a vehicle that allows the naïve to understand foreign experiences (“There is no frigate like a book…”) But at 16, I hardly understood my own life and struggled to appreciate how it resembled or differed from the books I read. Literature benefits multiplicatively from the richness of my own experiences. My teenage self could never have appreciated &lt;em&gt;Anna Karenina&lt;/em&gt; as much as I do now, five years into my marriage.
This is a compelling reason to reread books. I barely remembered &lt;em&gt;The Odyssey&lt;/em&gt;, but even if I remembered every line, rereading it with a new perspective would be worthwhile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Much of contemporary social science formalizes knowledge that we’ve had for a long time.&lt;/strong&gt; If I wanted to earn a PhD in behavioral economics, I would open a Jane Austen book to a random page, pick a random sentence, and then design a study that uses the behavior of a dozen Harvard undergrads to “prove” the wisdom contained in that sentence. Literature gets many things wrong, but the filter of centuries is far more exacting than peer review. The inhabitants of past centuries weren’t idiots, even if they couldn’t express their ideas in contemporary scientific language. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reading literature takes practice.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Anna Karenina&lt;/em&gt; is my favorite book I read last year, and it was unbelievably difficult to get though. The book took me 20 hours of reading time cover to cover, sprinkled across 9 months. (I took a few months off in the middle and then restarted from the beginning.) I couldn’t read it for more than about 45 minutes at a time without falling asleep or becoming restless. For years, I failed to cultivate my ability to concentrate on a single piece of writing, and so it atrophied. By the end of the year, though, I was simply better at reading. With reading as with running, I find that consistent practice allows me to move faster and keep at it for longer. And as with running, I hope to never be so “out of shape” again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Revealed preferences are real.&lt;/strong&gt; There was one particular Sunday morning last June that I earmarked for reading &lt;em&gt;Anna Karenina&lt;/em&gt;. I was on vacation and had nothing else to do. But instead of Russian literature, I found myself opening a copy of &lt;a href="https://web.stanford.edu/~hastie/ElemStatLearn/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Elements of Statistical Learning&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/a&gt; (It’s an iconic, ludicrously dense textbook that develops the mathematical foundations of machine learning.) I deeply believe that I’ve underinvested in reading literature and I’m proud of my effort to read more, but there’s a reason my degrees are in math and computer science rather than literature.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Structure is valuable.&lt;/strong&gt; Put this down as another lesson that I learned from reading and from running. I can absolutely guarantee that I wouldn’t have made it through &lt;em&gt;Anna Karenina&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;Crime and Punishment&lt;/em&gt; without having committed to both books beforehand. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Facebook is actually pretty great.&lt;/strong&gt; When I wrote my initial article about reading thirty books, I only shared it via Facebook. All sorts of people – friends, family members, and acquaintances – commented on my list and added their own suggestions. Strikingly, this didn’t just happen on Facebook. I had multiple conversations over the course of the year – with my uncle, or with a friend, or with a friend’s father – where they brought up the list I’d shared and added their own recommendations. It’s fashionable to hate on Facebook, and I only visit the site for a few minutes a few times a week, but it facilitated some of the most meaningful conversations I’ve had in the last year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lessons I listed above are more important than the actual checklist of results, but I do feel obligated to shared that progress report.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First off, I actually did find books for the last six slots:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Jorge Luis Borges: Labyrinths&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each of these short stories is deeply thought provoking. I enjoyed this one immensely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Tom Wolfe: The Electric Kool-Aid Acid Test&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tom Wolfe is one of my favorite authors, and while &lt;em&gt;The Right Stuff&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Bonfire of the Vanities&lt;/em&gt; are both superior to this book, it’s still worthwhile. There’s an unabashedly countercultural thread in Silicon Valley’s history that is no longer extant, and I wonder how the tech industry will be diminished as that legacy fades further into the past. That said, by the end of the book I was thoroughly tired of Ken Kesey and all of the Pranksters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;G.K. Chesterton: The Innocence of Father Brown&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another enjoyable compilation of thought-provoking short stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;James C. Scott: Seeing Like a State&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book left an impression that feels disproportionate to its quality. I thought the book was OK, and that it was at its best when it crystallized seemingly obvious ideas. However, since I finished the book, I’ve found myself constantly thinking about its themes. Here’s &lt;a href="http://writing.maxrosett.com/seeing-like-a-search-engine.html"&gt;a piece&lt;/a&gt; I wrote applying some of those arguments to understand Google's impact on the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Tyler Cowen: Big Business: A Love Letter to an American Anti-Hero&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read much of what Cowen writes and consider him an excellent thinker, which is why I feel comfortable saying this was well below his usual standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Pearl S Buck: The Good Earth&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read this book in high school and picked it up again on a whim. I got more out of it than the first time around, but I can’t recall thinking of it since I put it down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to these six books, I make a couple substitutions: Terry Pratchett’s &lt;em&gt;The Truth&lt;/em&gt; in exchange for &lt;em&gt;The Colour of Magic&lt;/em&gt;, and the entire George Smiley series in exchange for &lt;em&gt;Call For the Dead&lt;/em&gt;. John le Carre’s books became my default low-effort reading last year, and they filled that role admirably.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll also admit that I didn’t finish my whole list. The books I failed to read were largely ancient classics (I only finished &lt;em&gt;The Odyssey&lt;/em&gt;) or pieces of philosophy or criticism. I’m still working on &lt;em&gt;The Theory of Moral Sentiments&lt;/em&gt;, but it’s a challenging read. &lt;em&gt;The Closing of the American Mind&lt;/em&gt; was a surprisingly disappointing books, largely because the disputes it addresses – so relevant to the culture wars of the 80’s – all seem long resolved. In truth, I abandoned it after a tedious passage discussing the evils of the “orgasmic” rhythms of rock music. By contrast, the first chapter of &lt;em&gt;The Western Canon&lt;/em&gt; still feels extremely relevant. However, I skipped the bulk of the book since I got very little out of Bloom’s commentary on books I haven’t read. I’ll revisit this book in the future after reading more Shakespeare and Milton.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t stand the title character of &lt;em&gt;Emma&lt;/em&gt; and abandoned it half-way through. I may still force myself to finish it, though, if only to improve my knowledge of behavioral economics. Finally, I couldn’t find versions of the two Shakespeare plays that work well with my preferred formats (Audible or Kindle) and never got around to picking up physical versions. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m incredibly pleased that I put together and explicit reading list for last year, and I plan to compile a similar list for 2020, even if the year is well underway. Please let me know if you have any suggestions!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="books"></category></entry><entry><title>Seeing Like a Search Engine</title><link href="http://writing.maxrosett.com/seeing-like-a-search-engine.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-01-25T20:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-01-25T20:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Max Rosett</name></author><id>tag:writing.maxrosett.com,2020-01-25:/seeing-like-a-search-engine.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;James Scott’s &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Seeing-like-State-Certain-Condition/dp/0300078153"&gt;“Seeing Like a State”&lt;/a&gt; is a fascinating account of how centralization schemes fail. The book’s title follows from a simple observation: centralized administrators need legibility to function. A state can’t collect taxes unless it knows who its citizens are and how much income they’re …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;James Scott’s &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Seeing-like-State-Certain-Condition/dp/0300078153"&gt;“Seeing Like a State”&lt;/a&gt; is a fascinating account of how centralization schemes fail. The book’s title follows from a simple observation: centralized administrators need legibility to function. A state can’t collect taxes unless it knows who its citizens are and how much income they’re generating. A forester needs to know what trees are in the forest in order to extract lumber from it. The concept seems trivial but articulating the need for legibility facilitates clear thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the organic, natural state of things tends not to be legible. It’s hard to know what’s going on in a forest (not to mention a whole country.) In practice, administrators handle limited legibility in three ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They superimpose structures that make the world more legible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They reshape the world to make it more legible and assume that the complexity they’re removing is irrelevant.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When they fail to achieve perfect legibility, they focus on maximizing imperfect metrics while simply ignoring factors that aren’t easily visible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of these three approaches, the first tends to be harmless or even benign. Creating an accurate map of a forest has no impact on the forest itself. Standardizing weights and measures also makes society more legible to the government – the better to collect and assess taxes – but is also useful &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, the second approach can be incredibly destructive. Early scientific foresters liked the idea of planting orderly, monocropped forests that could be easily managed, but the resulting forests were highly susceptible to disease and ecological collapse. Similarly, centrally planned cities (like Brasília) are easy to administer but feel sterile to residents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third approach may be the most destructive of all. To again use a forestry example, it’s straightforward to optimize a single legible metric like annual timber production. But doing so can inflict hard-to-measure damage along other dimensions, like the health or aesthetic appeal of the forest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The governmental analogy is obvious. Soviet production quotas invariably failed to capture important qualities of the products that were being produced. As a result, they were endlessly gamed. Perhaps the best-known story is of a nail factory producing gigantic, useless nails to achieve a production target measured in tons. While that example appears to be apocryphal, others are &lt;a href="https://skeptics.stackexchange.com/questions/22375/did-a-soviet-nail-factory-produce-useless-nails-to-improve-metrics"&gt;well-documented&lt;/a&gt;, and as a more general rule Soviet products were hardly known for their quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The entire book is interesting, and I recommend that you read it (or at least read a more thorough summary of it, like &lt;a href="https://www.ribbonfarm.com/2010/07/26/a-big-little-idea-called-legibility/"&gt;Venkatesh Rao's&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2017/03/16/book-review-seeing-like-a-state/"&gt;Scott Alexander's&lt;/a&gt;.) As I discussed the book with the friends who recommended it, my one complaint was that the analysis draws heavily on examples from two domains, forestry and government central planning, and I would have liked to see examples in other contexts. And then it struck me that the most obvious example was right in front of me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What does this have to do with Google?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scott published his book in 1998, which is the year that Google was founded. Like a state or a forester, Google requires a high degree of legibility to deliver its tremendously useful service. Fortunately for Google, the internet is inherently more legible than the real world, and so they were able to successfully build the early version of their search engine without any need to reshape the internet into legible form. For the briefest of moments, Google was just another observer with no real power to shape the rest of the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Google and its ambition grew, though, it started exerting influence over the internet to make it more legible. Much of this was benign. Webmasters adding sitemaps to their sites made the internet more legible to Google (and by extension more useful to the rest of us) without inflicting any real harm. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the field of search engine optimization (SEO) developed, though, the internet started shaping itself to Google’s needs in more destructive ways. There’s been a proliferation of content that seems to only be intended for reading by Google. A trivial example comes from a recipe for spinach enchiladas that I recently encountered. The page contained a 433-word preamble, 19 of which were “enchilada.”  Far from improving my experience with the (quite delicious) recipe, they made the page much less useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A far more profound example is Google’s Accelerated Mobile Pages (AMP) project. AMP is a tightly limited set of web components that publishers can use to build pages. The resulting pages are usually (&lt;a href="https://unlikekinds.com/article/google-amp-page-speed"&gt;but not always&lt;/a&gt;) 
 faster to load which benefits users. Publishers who use AMP benefit as well, as Google gives AMP pages significantly better placement in search results. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The benefit to Google, though, is that AMP pages are highly legible. The reduced component set makes them easy to crawl, and the inclusion of structured data makes it very easy to extract information from the page. Furthermore, Google can cache the pages and serve them from their own servers, thereby learning about how users interact with the content. (This is why you’ll sometimes see google.com in the URL for articles that you access on a mobile device.) The bottom line is that AMP makes the internet more legible to Google.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has prompted some backlash, with one &lt;a href="https://www.polemicdigital.com/google-amp-go-to-hell/"&gt;polemical piece&lt;/a&gt; pointing out that “the web is a messy, complicated place” and negatively comparing the organic parts of the internet to “the Google-shaped web.” &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lens of legibility is also useful for understanding where Google Search delivers sub-par performance. Yesterday, I was looking for a simple tool to plot out a running route. The top results were all useless: poor interfaces, a requirement to sign up for the service, etc. I finally found what I was looking for at the bottom of the front page. Of course, those flaws are completely illegible to Google. They can observe symptoms of those flaws – a quick bounce rate when I visit the page, for instance – but they don’t really have a way to understand what makes one run-mapping tool better than another.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These areas of illegibility tend to overlap with commerce. Anything that lives in the real world – whether apartments, tea kettles, clothing – is inherently illegible to web crawlers. Google can employ some basic filtering, like responding to “apartments with Denver” with links to listings that are indeed in Denver, but the actual qualities that make an apartment appealing to the searcher are entirely opaque to Google. The first page of results usually has the best link somewhere, but it’s rarely the top result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Seeing Like a State&lt;/em&gt; emphasizes the tragic consequences of states seeking after and failing to achieve legibility. Scott repeatedly uses the USSR as an example. That made me hesitant to write this piece, because I do not intend to compare Google – my former employer - to the Soviet Union. If nothing else, Google lacks the coercive power of a state, and its web crawlers are limited to a narrow domain. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But within that domain – the Internet – Google is as powerful as any state, and its crucial to understand Google’s need for legibility. When left unchecked, the need for legibility favors the orderly over the organic and the simple over the complex. But organic complexity is precisely what makes the internet so remarkable. We’ve already lost some of the free-form vibrancy of the early internet, and I fear that the quest for legibility will perpetuate that trend.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="google"></category><category term="seo"></category><category term="books"></category></entry><entry><title>Why Users Don't Complain About "The Google Squeeze"</title><link href="http://writing.maxrosett.com/google-ad-load.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-11-14T20:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-14T20:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Max Rosett</name></author><id>tag:writing.maxrosett.com,2019-11-14:/google-ad-load.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ben Thompson's characteristically excellent &lt;a href="https://stratechery.com/2019/the-google-squeeze/"&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; this week focuses on how Google has forced online travel agencies (like Expedia) to pay for traffic by prioritizing ads and pushing organic results further down the page. Part of this is clear product improvements, like a paid-inclusion hotel module that's useful to users while …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ben Thompson's characteristically excellent &lt;a href="https://stratechery.com/2019/the-google-squeeze/"&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; this week focuses on how Google has forced online travel agencies (like Expedia) to pay for traffic by prioritizing ads and pushing organic results further down the page. Part of this is clear product improvements, like a paid-inclusion hotel module that's useful to users while generating revenue for Google. But some of it is just increased ad load. Certain search terms have seen the number of ads before the first organic result double, from two to four, over the last several years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ben glosses over why users haven't resisted this and says that the ads are easy to ignore. I think the reality is more interesting and more complex. Simply put, Google's paid results for certain commercial terms just aren't that much worse than the organic results. That's because the signals Google uses for organic search aren't that useful in context (and companies are spend millions of dollars to improve those signals), so the signal a site sends by paying for placement is arguably just as useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't have any experience working with OTAs, but I used to work in a vertical (online apartment listings) where providers are also reliant on Google for both paid and organic traffic. I'm not an expert on search engines, but my experience gave some insight into why Google has been able to increase ad load so aggressively without ruining user experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's review how Google sorts results for a search term. There are many factors, but at a high level, Google will prioritize pages based on two factors: a) relevant content and b) inbound links from high-quality sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This works great when you search for "make my cat stop stealing my food" and get a top result that is a) a long essay on the subject and b) gets lots of links from other sites because, after all, it is the seminal work on thwarting feline food theft. Crucially, you're searching for &lt;em&gt;text&lt;/em&gt;, and Google can do a pretty good job of figuring out if a page contains the text you're looking for. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a term like "apartments in washington dc", though, things fall apart. The content you're looking for isn't an essay; it's apartment listings. And while Google can do a decent job of understanding if text is relevant, it has no way evaluate the quality of those listings. And even if Google &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; evaluate the quality of listings, all of the big apartment websites have listings for the exact same professionally managed buildings. (The same is true with OTAs: booking.com has roughly the same hotels as hotels.com.) So Google ordering results based on content is basically a no-go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the content half of Google's formula doesn't work for apartment listings, what about the inbound link half? Well, websites work &lt;em&gt;really hard&lt;/em&gt; to get links to pages they care about. This is a key part of the practice known as search engine optimization (SEO). For instance, at my old job, we'd reach out to universities in Washington, DC and ask them to link to our DC page on their housing guide. Or we'd write a report on rent trends in DC, put it on our listing page, and then email reporters in the hope that they'd link to that page. In either case, getting the inbound link was only vaguely related to actually having high-quality listings on our page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite these flaws, Google's organic results for "apartments in washington dc" are pretty accurate. That's because SEO has a meaningful signaling component. The links we got to our Washington, DC page had little to do with the quality of the listings, but they did show Google that we were a competent organization with a significant budget available to invest in SEO and a particular interest in promoting our DC page. All of those attributes were (loosely) correlated with having good listings on that. In our case, we had just signed new partners in the DC area and were eager to drive traffic to the new buildings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, if you're a competent organization that's willing to spend a lot of money to promote a particular page (and SEO does cost a lot of money) then perhaps Google should simply collect that money from you directly. "We'll pay Google a million dollars a year for traffic" is just as compelling a signal as "we'll spend a million dollars a year on our SEO team." You do occasionally get wildly irrelevant ads, mostly when some small site messes up their targeting, but search ads are expensive and advertisers care a lot about only showing their ads on relevant searches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To go back to our example term of "apartments in washington dc", three of the four ads are totally interchangeable with the top four organic results. (Indeed, apartments.com is currently both the top organic result and the top ad.) The fourth is an ad for a company that provides furnished apartments in DC. That ad is less relevant to the average searcher, but it's not offensively so, and in some cases it may be even more relevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To return to Ben's article, he writes, "the SEO channel is free, the hotel module isn’t." That's incorrect. SEO amounts to paying an army of freelance writers, link builders, and marketing experts to drive traffic to you on Google. Once you realize that, it's natural for Google to just collect the money directly. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disclosure: I worked as a software engineer at Google after I worked in the apartment industry. However, I didn't work in the search division, and I have no insider knowledge about the search algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="google"></category><category term="ads"></category><category term="seo"></category></entry><entry><title>Startup Stock Options: How Did a Good Deal Go Bad?</title><link href="http://writing.maxrosett.com/startup-stock-options-bad-deal.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-04-11T08:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-04-11T08:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Max Rosett</name></author><id>tag:writing.maxrosett.com,2019-04-11:/startup-stock-options-bad-deal.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the &lt;a href="https://steveblank.com/2019/04/10/startup-stock-options-why-a-good-deal-has-gone-bad/"&gt;top posts&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=19624164"&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt; yesterday made the point that stock options aren't a great deal for startup employees these days. That thesis is entirely correct and is quickly becoming conventional wisdom around Palo Alto. But I raised my eyebrows at the article's description of the cause …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the &lt;a href="https://steveblank.com/2019/04/10/startup-stock-options-why-a-good-deal-has-gone-bad/"&gt;top posts&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=19624164"&gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt; yesterday made the point that stock options aren't a great deal for startup employees these days. That thesis is entirely correct and is quickly becoming conventional wisdom around Palo Alto. But I raised my eyebrows at the article's description of the cause:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;VCs have intentionally changed the ~50-year-old social contract with startup employees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I this is inaccurate or at least incomplete. VCs are providing the funding that lets companies stay private indefinitely, and that has driven down the practical value of stock options. But two other key factors that are far beyond the control of investors. One is a technical change to a the tax code; the other is the out-of-control cost of living in the Bay Area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's start with the tax issue. Since the 80's, the IRS has required companies to grant options with strike prices at the "fair market value" of the shares, but initially they didn't define "fair market value."  So prior to the early 2000's, startups could issue stock options (for common stock) with exercise prices dramatically below the prices paid by investors for preferred shares. The rule of thumb was to issue options with a share price of just 10% (!) of the investor price. That deal worked pretty well for both employees and the startups. Employees got options that were far more likely to actually be worth something, while companies could provide tremendous value to employees in exchange for relatively little equity. To top it off, the income from those options was frequently taxed at the (much lower) capital gains rate. The only downside of the low strike price for either party was that the company received less cash at the time of exercise, but if that happened in parallel with an acquisition or IPO, it hardly mattered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a series of rule changes, though, the IRS cracked down on this. This &lt;a href="https://www.teknosassociates.com/how-changes-in-regulation-have-driven-stock-option-prices/"&gt;abbreviated history&lt;/a&gt; is interesting in a dry, "I can't believe I'm reading about the history of the tax code" kind of way. The bottom line is that employee stock options today have strike prices very similar to the share prices investors pay. That represents an over-correction. Common stock is probably worth more than 10% the value of preferred shares - which is why stock options were so valuable 20 years ago - but now we're in a world where employees at companies with "successful" exits still see their options become worthless. A company's value has to go up a lot (30%? 50%?) before a new hire's options really start capturing value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has huge implications for a company's compensation strategy. Holding &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; except tax regulations constant, &lt;strong&gt;options are now worth a fraction of what they used to be.&lt;/strong&gt; As a result, companies that give the exact same options (liquidation preferences, time to liquidity, etc) to employees now provide them with a fraction of the value. Prior to 2000, the most efficient way for a company to deploy its equity was to offer it directly to employees as compensation. Apparently in 2019, the most efficient use of equity is to sell it to investors and pay employees higher salaries with the proceeds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the backdrop for all of this is growing Bay Area housing prices and the not-entirely-unrelated growth in engineer salaries. Options have become less valuable at precisely the same time that employees need a lot more cash just to maintain a basic standard of living. They also have better access to that cash than ever before: Facebook, Apple, and Google seem happy to pay senior engineers half a million dollars in cash + fully liquid stock. The story isn't about VCs and startups unilaterally reducing the attractiveness of options packages. It &lt;em&gt;couldn't&lt;/em&gt; be. The hiring market in the Bay Area is really competitive; if employees wanted to take lower salaries in exchange for meaningful options packages, they'd get it. But Palantir is the only company I know of that significantly reduces cash compensation to make options (or options-like equity instruments) a core piece of compensation packages, and even they have seen employee frustration over that at times. If anyone knows of other companies that heavily weight options (as opposed to RSUs) in their compensation, I'd be curious to hear about them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Speaking of Palantir, the long time to IPO isn't necessarily as much as a problem as it seems. In addition to internal share buybacks, various hedge funds and secondary buyers have stepped in to fill that hole; my friends at Palantir receive constant LinkedIn messages from would-be purchasers. In Silicon Valley c.a. 1999, a company would reach a few hundred million dollars in valuation, IPO, and provide liquidity for employees. The current model seems to be that companies reach the billion dollar mark and then undergo a shadow IPO where they raise a ton of money from SoftBank and their employees start getting liquidity from private investors. It's not a perfect solution, but it's a solution.) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if the decline in the relevance of options isn't entirely the fault of investors and companies, they don't seem to have done much to fight against it. Investors get byzantine liquidity preferences that make it hard for employees to understand the value of their shares. 90-day exercise windows create cash crunches for employees who leave even if they're fully vested. What I find particularly grating is founders arranging to sell their own shares as part of funding rounds while denying employees that same opportunity. Liquidity is a real problem; I have exactly no idea what to do with the shares I own from my last company. The original article's suggestions seem like they would help. Specifically, more companies should grant RSUs and provide employees with chances to sell vested shares. I don't know if that can perfectly recreate the upside-oriented alignment of incentives generated by stock options 20 years ago. But it would be a start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again - the collapsing value of options is a huge problem for Silicon Valley startups. My one sentence version of economics is "people respond to incentives", and options have historically done a great job of aligning incentives. If the changes to the tax code mean that options can't play that role anymore, then Sand Hill Road had better come up with something that can.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="startups"></category><category term="stock options"></category><category term="Silicon Valley"></category></entry><entry><title>Book Review: The Things They Carried</title><link href="http://writing.maxrosett.com/book-review-things-they-carried.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-03-04T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-03-04T12:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Max Rosett</name></author><id>tag:writing.maxrosett.com,2019-03-04:/book-review-things-they-carried.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Vietnam War is foreign to me.  My father was far too young to be drafted, as he was in elementary school when the war ended. By the time I was that age, Vietnam had opened itself to foreign tourists. To my generation of Americans, Vietnam is an exotic vacation …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Vietnam War is foreign to me.  My father was far too young to be drafted, as he was in elementary school when the war ended. By the time I was that age, Vietnam had opened itself to foreign tourists. To my generation of Americans, Vietnam is an exotic vacation or perhaps somewhere to live for a year after college. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Historical events fade from collective memory, but for the certified "bad war" the process is closer to a scrubbing. I only encounter the Vietnam War when I see the words "Vietnam Vet" scrawled in Sharpie on a homeless man's cardboard sign. World War II feels much closer, with Pearl Harbor, D-Day, and other anniversaries commemorated each year. There are no similar remembrances of the Vietnam War, and in truth I don't even know what days would be equivalent. If pressed, I can generate names like "The Gulf of Tonkin" and "Tet Offensive", but I don't understand the narrative of the war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first read the titular story of &lt;em&gt;The Things They Carried&lt;/em&gt; as a high school freshman in my dad's English class, and I remembered the story clearly even before picking it up last month. Reading it this time gave the jarring sensation of looking at something familiar with new eyes. To a fourteen-year-old, Lieutenant Jimmy Cross's obsession with Martha's virginity signified an adult proximity to sex that I could only imagine. Consciously, I recognized his folly in blaming himself for Ted Lavender's death. But how could I ascribe that folly to his youth and innocence when I possessed the same traits in greater quantity?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stories are fiction, but, as O'Brien writes, "story-truth is sometimes truer than happening-truth." Grand strategy makes no appearance in this book about experience, and I know nothing more of the Tet Offensive than before I read it.  Instead, as the title promises, I know the burdens carried by the men of Alpha Company. They lived in fear of sudden death and they lived in the mud that's ubiquitous in anti-war novels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;O'Brien in particular carries his own moral failings. He explicitly believes that the war was pointless and amoral. Simply by going of to war (rather than fleeing to Canada or risking prison) he showed his own cowardice and weakness. Clearly, that's why he was still writing about the war twenty years after returning home. "A true war story is never moral," he writes, and amoral stories rarely feel complete. When he writes of characters who survived the war but never truly returned home, he is of course speaking of himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The theme of cowardice and weakness run throughout the book. If only O'Brien had been stronger, he could have saved Kiowa as he drowned in a field of shit. If only he'd been braver, he could have refused to fight and to kill. The insistence on blaming himself for so much of the bad (just as Jimmy Cross does) is his feeble attempt to assert some slight degree of control over what happened. It's easier to accept blame for such catastrophes than to acknowledge that they were far beyond your influence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stories in &lt;em&gt;The Things They Carried&lt;/em&gt; stand in stark contrast to how I spent my early adulthood. I lived the rarefied life of an Ivy League student, and I was never shot at in the jungles of Vietnam. But the difference is not quite so clear. My own brush with mortality came when I was diagnosed with melanoma at 20, and a quick glance at statistics suggests that the cancer was easily an order of magnitude more dangerous than deployment to Vietnam. Undoubtedly, I carry that trauma, and I thought of it frequently as I read the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then, in the final story, the author draws the same parallel. The final story in this collection about Vietnam is instead about his childhood sweetheart Linda, who died of a brain tumor at age nine. He writes that he keeps Linda alive by telling her story, just as he does for Kiowa and Ted Lavender and all the others. But O'Brien is too haunted for me to take that explanation at face value. Once again, he dwells on his moral failure to stand up to Nick Veenhof, a classmate who teased Linda for wearing a red hat to cover her balding head. But of course, O'Brien was powerless to stop a child bully, and even more powerless to stop the cancer that killed her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;War is not unique in its ability to inflict senseless suffering and misery. But for O'Brien, the war revealed and expanded his moral failings in a way that vastly outstripped the trauma of any one experience. The horror, the horror...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout this review, I've used the word "read." That's not entirely accurate; I actually listened to the Audible recording of this book, read by Bryan Cranston. I highly recommend it. Bryan Cranston is a brilliant reader, and some stories are meant to be told orally. Additionally, the recording includes an hour long non-fiction piece written and read by Tim O'Brien about his return to Vietnam in the early 90's. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's &lt;a href="http://writing.maxrosett.com/thirty-books-before-thirty.html"&gt;what I wrote&lt;/a&gt; about why I wanted to read this book last December. It succeeded on both counts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm interested in this collection of short stories for two reasons. First, the Vietnam War was a defining experience for a generation of Americans, and I don't know much about it. Second, I enjoy well-executed creative writing, and by all accounts this book fits that description.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="books"></category><category term="history"></category><category term="creative writing"></category></entry><entry><title>Book Review: The Elephant in the Brain</title><link href="http://writing.maxrosett.com/book-review-elephant-in-the-brain.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-02-10T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-02-10T12:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Max Rosett</name></author><id>tag:writing.maxrosett.com,2019-02-10:/book-review-elephant-in-the-brain.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This book convincingly demonstrates that we humans constantly deceive others and ourselves alike in the service of our own selfish motives. What's less clear is what implications follow from that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book is divided into two sections. The first lays out the immense array of ways in which humans are …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This book convincingly demonstrates that we humans constantly deceive others and ourselves alike in the service of our own selfish motives. What's less clear is what implications follow from that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book is divided into two sections. The first lays out the immense array of ways in which humans are selfish, deceitful animals.  The authors' perspective is Hobbesian, except they don't think that civilization has really done much to civilize us. We're in a constant struggle with each other for status, sex, and supporters, and in fact our cognitive abilities probably evolved to help us in that struggle (rather than to help us deal with non-human threats.) We lie, cheat, manipulate, and so on while working hard to rationalize our own motives.  The arguments are compelling and well-written, with lots of analogies drawn between our behavior and the behavior of various animals. They do seem to view all forms of signaling as somehow dishonest, which is strange. After all, signals contain information!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hanson and Simler then argue that the first victim of the brain's deception is itself, and again they present compelling evidence. For instance, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Split-brain"&gt;split-brain patients&lt;/a&gt; who have their motives hidden from them develop false rationalizations on the fly. They take things a step further, though, arguing that the purpose of our self-deceit is to better deceive others:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our brains are built to act in our self-interest while at the same time trying hard not to appear selfish in front of other people. And in order to thrown them of the trail, our brains often keep "us," our conscious minds, in the dark. The less we know of our own ugly motives, the easier it is to hide them from others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a radical claim, but they're not able to marshal much hard evidence to support it. As they acknowledge, the theory was first proposed more than 40 years ago, and while it's intriguing, it's hard incontrovertible. Their efforts to demonstrate it end up feeling like a "just-so" story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having argued for the primacy of hidden motives, the authors spend the second half of the book examining how that impacts everyday life. The have chapters on education, conversation, and the healthcare system. Portions of this second section are insightful, but others are less compelling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take the example of healthcare. The authors convincingly argue that health care is not, as most people say, simply about getting healthy.  Under what they term the "conspicuous caring hypothesis", much of healthcare is a performative attempt to show support for someone who is unwell. Thus we spend far too much on spectacular interventions and end-of-life care while dismissing non-medical interventions (like improving air quality) that are far more cost-effective. Healthcare does make people healthier, they allow, but the demand for conspicuous caring induces tremendous inefficiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They view this last point as cause for optimism:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This may sound like pessimism, but it's actually great news. However flawed our institutions may be, we're already living with them--and life, for most of us, is pretty good. So if we can accurately diagnose what's holding back our institutions, we may finally succeed in reforming them, thereby making our lives even better. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That strikes me as precisely backwards. It's well known that there's a lot of medical spending that doesn't seem to improve health. If the only purpose of the medical system were to make people healthy, then we might have a path to cutting  spending while simultaneously impoving outcomes. But if what patients genuinely want is to feel like extravagant effort is being put into taking care of them... well, then we have a less tractable problem. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, it's not clear that the purpose of the healthcare system &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be to improve healthcare outcomes, narrowly defined. When I had melanoma, my goal was to recover to full health, and to that end I was treated by two oncologists. One was consistently empathetic, and even when he delivered bad news I felt empowered. The other casually suggested that my disease may have returned and then left the room without so much as a comforting word. (Twenty minutes later, a nurse was surprised to find me still in the room and said I could leave.) I have no way of knowing which physician is better in the narrow, technical sense. But assume the latter is slightly superior. Would it be wrong of me to still prefer the former, even if that ran contrary to my stated goal? Or, to take it a step further: If presented with evidence that the unpleasant oncologist was the superior clinician, I'd probably rationalize it away to avoid cognitive discord. Does that action invalidate my preference?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mind you, there's plenty of waste in the healthcare system, and we should work hard to remove that. But effort that doesn't align with the stated (or perhaps straw-manned) purpose of the institution is not inherently wasted effort. Conversely, the cause of waste isn't necessarily hidden motives. Healthcare spending in the US is a) tax-deductible, b) paid for in ways that lead to zero marginal cost to consumers as the consume tremendous resources and c) incredibly opaquely priced. &lt;em&gt;Of course&lt;/em&gt; there's going to be a lot of waste!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's easy to demonstrate that someone's revealed preferences differ from what they tell you. You can even demonstrate that those preferences are inconsistent and irrational. It's much harder to tell them that their preferences are &lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt;. We still do it often enough, and at times it's justifiable, but the barrier is much higher than simply demonstrating irrationality. Simler and Hanson assume that being healthy is a rational goal and wanting conspicuous caring is irrational, but why is that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's value to recognizing the disparity between the stated purpose of an institution and its actual purpose. Economists have long argued that education is mostly about signaling rather than, you know, education. This has big policy implications. For instance, subsizing college education makes a lot of sense if you think it develops human capital. It makes a lot less sense if you see education as a sorting exercise. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this can only take you so far. The book demonstrates that education isn't really about education; it's some strange mix of signaling, sorting, babysitting, and a dating service, perhaps all hosted on the grounds of a vaguely related research facility. You can eliminate those superfluous components and deliver the education itself at a fraction of the cost, and that's great! (It's how I got my MS from Georgia Tech, in fact.) It turns out, though, that society largely wants college to have all of those pieces. Professors, lawmakers, and students all deceive themselves by talking about "education" when they really mean a bunch of things that aren't education. But if we all deceive ourselves in the same way, doesn't that induce a strange consistency? We can go on building the institution we actually want, regardless of if it matches our stated purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, the book is most compelling as a tool for examining your own thoughts. You already know that you deceive to others about your motives. With a bit more introspection, you can understand how you're deceiving yourself. In the conclusion, the authors advocate for the philosophy of "enlightened self-interest" which calls to acknowledge your own selfish motives and harness them to do genuine good. I wish they'd developed that theme further; I think the philosophical implications of hidden motives are more compelling than the implications for institutions like healthcare and education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In that spirit, I should examine my own motives for writing this post. I tell myself that a) I enjoy writing and b)I want to share my thoughts with others. Digging deeper on b), a more precise framing is "share my thoughts with others so that they'll raise my status appropriately." There may be deeper motives as well, but for now they remain opaque to me.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="books"></category><category term="psychology"></category><category term="rationality"></category></entry><entry><title>Economists and Skiing</title><link href="http://writing.maxrosett.com/skiing-economists-and-stoke-returns.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-12-28T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-12-28T12:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Max Rosett</name></author><id>tag:writing.maxrosett.com,2018-12-28:/skiing-economists-and-stoke-returns.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Each winter morning, hordes of parka-clad addicts descend on the ski resorts that dot the mountains of the western US. They share one goal: allocating their time to maximize stoke levels at the moment they return to the lodge. The skiers employ a wide range of strategies to optimize these …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Each winter morning, hordes of parka-clad addicts descend on the ski resorts that dot the mountains of the western US. They share one goal: allocating their time to maximize stoke levels at the moment they return to the lodge. The skiers employ a wide range of strategies to optimize these so-called "stoke returns." Chairlifts overflow with self-described experts who claim unique approaches for achieving the best results. Sadly, many are little more than charlatans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a sad fact of life that an individual's stoke returns are largely driven by mountain conditions. A harsh drought can drive stoke returns so low that many skiers slide into depression. Conversely, ideal mountain conditions benefit everyone who visits. In either scenario, though, some skiers achieve higher stoke levels than others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly, many economists devote their careers to understanding which factors drive the variation in returns. The first breakthrough occurred when a group of economists visited Alta in the 1960s. Over their two week visit, they noticed that they could achieve consistent albeit modest stoke returns by sticking to the safer parts of the mountain. Stoke varied minimally with snowfall levels because groomed parts of the mountain almost always remain skiable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, skiers who take on more risk seem to capture higher average returns. Venturing off trail gives skiers access to solitude, challenging terrain, and the miraculous form of upside known as "powder days." But it also exposes them to stoke-destroying catastrophes: embarrassing crashes, injuries, and the shame of taking off their skis and hiking 100 yards back up the mountain to avoid a cliff. Furthermore, skiers who commit to this strategy are prone to sulking in the lodge in dry conditions, thereby forfeiting the modest stoke returns of skiing groomers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Careful empirical analysis found that expected stoke returns increased as a linear function of risk. Indeed, variations in risk-seeking explained about 70% of the variation in returns across skiers. The single-factor model became a skiing industry standard, and a rich vocabulary developed around it. For instance, a skier who takes outsized risk in exchange for marginal stoke is said to have a high "Scar Ratio."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the 1990s, the single-factor model was ripe for improvement. Following a month-long visit to Snowbird, a team of University of Chicago economists proposed a three-factor model. Risk remained important, but they introduced two addtional factors: boot value and grooming levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyone who has ever jammed his foot into the plastic vice known as a ski boot will appreciate the importance of boot value. Indeed, the failure of economists to recognize it earlier reflects poorly on their profession.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By contrast, the impact of grooming on stoke returns is more subtle. Skiers seeking more risk have always been drawn to ungroomed, off-trail terrain. The breakthrough of the three-factor model was to recognize that even after holding risk levels constant, skiers can achieve higher stoke returns by allocating more time to low cat-utilization parts of the mountain. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, the three-factor model is the most widely accepted theory among alpine economists. Practitioners, of course, have their own perspective. Overcrowding is a real problem; no matter how great your strategy looks on paper, it will be ruined if swarms of other skiers execute on it at the same time. On the other hand, stoke seekers rely on techniques that are still controversial in the academic community. Some skiers have achieved great returns by focusing on maintaining high momentum, although critics say this increases the risk of running into a Cliff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the subtleties of maximizing stoke returns, most economists believe that anyone can achieve good returns over a long time horizon by skiing all parts of the mountain and maintaining modest levels of risk. And while critics occasionally claim that skier stoke levels are irrational, a morning of skiing invariably silences them. So it was that on a recent powder day, one naysayer was heard yelling "Rational exuberance!" as he floated through the unblemished snow.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="skiing"></category><category term="finance"></category></entry><entry><title>Cryptocurrency: A Failed Regulatory Innovation</title><link href="http://writing.maxrosett.com/cryptocurrency-regulatory-innovation.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-12-21T22:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-12-21T22:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Max Rosett</name></author><id>tag:writing.maxrosett.com,2018-12-21:/cryptocurrency-regulatory-innovation.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The cryptocurrency ecosytem passed an interesting milestone in mid-November when the SEC &lt;a href="https://www.sec.gov/news/press-release/2018-264"&gt;settled charges&lt;/a&gt; against two companies that had conducted ICOs. The SEC had previous taken action in connection with ICOs, but those were primarily textbook examples of fraud (guaranteed returns, founders absconding with proceeds, etc.) Those earlier enforcement actions …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The cryptocurrency ecosytem passed an interesting milestone in mid-November when the SEC &lt;a href="https://www.sec.gov/news/press-release/2018-264"&gt;settled charges&lt;/a&gt; against two companies that had conducted ICOs. The SEC had previous taken action in connection with ICOs, but those were primarily textbook examples of fraud (guaranteed returns, founders absconding with proceeds, etc.) Those earlier enforcement actions effectively said "A con doesn't become legal simply because you slapped the label ICO on it." &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This gave ICO advocates hope that "legitimate" ICOs would escape regulatory scrutiny. Outright fraud is more morally repulsive than technical violations of securities law, and the SEC's initial responses to ICOs focused on the outright scams. The November enforcement actions, however, demonstrate that the SEC takes security laws quite seriously. ICO proponents had framed them as a &lt;em&gt;technical&lt;/em&gt; breakthrough that would permit projects to raise capital in a low-friction way. In light of the SEC's decision, it's perhaps better to primarily view them as a (failed) regulatory innovation that lowered friction by simply ignoring the relevant laws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a common theme for applications of cryptocurrency. Enthusisasts talk about blockchain as a technical breakthrough that allows for a pseudonymous, decentralized, and censorship-resisitant currency. And as a software engineer who has worked with Bitcoin, I appreciate aesthetically how elegantly Bitcoin's protocol leads to those properties. But technical sophistication doesn't lead to billions of dollars of market cap. In the Bitcoin case, that value followed from properties that facilitated skirting regulations or outright breaking the law. After all, the first "killer" use for Bitcoin was anonymously buying hard drugs from strangers on the internet. That use case alone was enough to drive Bitcoin to several billion dollars in value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, Bitcoin enthusiasts continue to tout how it allows anyone to anonymously and frictionlessly send money to anyone in the world. And indeed, banks haven't built consumer-facing ways to easily send money to people in other countries. But moving money across borders isn't a technical problem. Certainly Chase has no problem doing so when I use my ATM card in Tokyo. The bigger hurdle is compliance with regulations and specifically anti-money laundering (AML) laws. Indeed, while it remains technically trivial to send Bitcoin in any country, it's become steadily harder to convert bitcoin to currency in countries that enforce typical banking regulations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The association of cryptocurrency with illegal activity isn't a reason to outright dismiss the technology. Many of the most popular tech companies today started off by facilitating illegal activity. Uber and Airbnb are obvious examples, and Youtube was a mess of pirated content in its early days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But companies that overtly break the law are in a precarious position. The success stories are the companies that meet authorities in the middle. Uber's overwhelming popularity with riders and drivers undermined support for burdensome taxi regulations, and most cities and states changed their laws correspondingly. In exchange, Uber began complying with the more modest regulations that cities passed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's hard to see a similar scenario playing out for cryptocurrency. I don't have strong opinions on whether or not security laws should be relaxed, but the poor track record of ICOs hasn't made a compelling case for it. (Note that adverse selection is a factor here; many ICOs seem to have attracted the same crowd that ran the penny stock scams of yesterday.) With most tokens trading below issue price, I doubt there's a groundswell of support for changing securities laws to legalize unregistered ICOs. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, while anti-money laundering laws can seem heavy handed, they serve more compelling purposes than your average taxi regulations c.a. 2008. Countries created AML laws with the intention of fighting some combination of drug trafficking, terrorism funding, and organized crime. Politically speaking, that gives regulators little incentive to meet cryptocurrency companies in the middle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The genuine technological breakthroughs behind Bitcoin and Ethereum led to widespread opportunities to push against a range of financial regulations. Similarly, the ubiquity of smartphones gave Uber the technological leverage to undermine antiquated taxi regulation (and to capture tremendous value in the process.) Unlike Uber, though, cryptocurrency enthusiasts have found regulators to be largely uncompromising. At this point, if the larger blockchain project is to make lasting impact on the world, it will have to do so through applications other than cryptocurrency.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="technology"></category><category term="bitcoin"></category><category term="cryptocurrency"></category><category term="blockchain"></category></entry><entry><title>Thirty Books I Want to Read Before I Turn Thirty</title><link href="http://writing.maxrosett.com/thirty-books-before-thirty.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-12-08T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-12-08T12:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Max Rosett</name></author><id>tag:writing.maxrosett.com,2018-12-08:/thirty-books-before-thirty.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently turned 29, and in honor of that milestone I've assembled a list of thirty books I'd like to read before I turn 30.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the end of high school until a few years ago, I undervalued books. I mostly consumed writing I found online. Online articles can be …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently turned 29, and in honor of that milestone I've assembled a list of thirty books I'd like to read before I turn 30.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the end of high school until a few years ago, I undervalued books. I mostly consumed writing I found online. Online articles can be a decent substitute for books on non-fiction topics of immediate interest, but only rarely do they touch on the human condition in a deep way. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading online content also tends to be a haphazard experience. The upside of that is serendipity, but as I look at gaps in my own knowledge and thinking, I appreciate the value of deliberate undertakings. For those reasons, I've set out to structure my reading for the next year around classic works of fiction and (to a lesser extent) philosophy. I might be better off making my way through the reading list of some great books course, but there's merit in constructing my own list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've provided brief explanations of why I want to read each book, but these explanations are necessarily speculative. I suspect in some cases I'm very wrong about what I'll get from reading the book. In some cases, the only reason I have for reading the book is that people I trust have recommended it. But what better reason could I have?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Classics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Homer: &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/The-Odyssey/dp/B07GL4J6Z1/ref=dp_kinw_strp_adbl_v2"&gt;The Odyssey&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read the Odyssey in 8th grade and it didn't make much of an impression. That was half a lifetime ago; I think I'll get much more from it this time. The timing works out well: Emily Wilson's recently released translation has good reviews, and the Audible version is performed by Claire Daines. I listen to a lot of audibooks simply for convenience, but since the Odyssey comes from an oral tradition I think there's an actual benefit to hearing it performed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Homer: &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/The-Odyssey/dp/B07GL4J6Z1/ref=dp_kinw_strp_adbl_v2"&gt;The Iliad&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've never read the Iliad and would like to complete the pair. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Virgil: &lt;a href="https://www.audible.com/pd/The-Aeneid-Audiobook/B002VA9BZC"&gt;The Aeneid&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Aeneid honestly seems to be an inferior version of the Odyssey, but that's probably just me revealing my preference for the Greeks over the Romans. Regardless, I've never read it, and I may as well get a complete accounting of all those who got lost on their way home from Troy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Thucydides: &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Landmark-Thucydides/dp/1416590870/ref=mt_hardcover?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;me=&amp;amp;qid="&gt;The Peloponessian War&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book is the reason I'm including links to what I plan to read. I have a copy of &lt;em&gt;The Peloponessian War&lt;/em&gt; upstairs, but it lacks the maps and annotations that make the Landmark edition so engaging. I took an undergraduate seminar on the Peloponnesian War, but I'm eager to revisit Thucydides with an additional nine years of perspective. Fear, Honor, Interest...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Fiction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;William Shakespeare: &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Hamlet-Thrift-Editions-William-Shakespeare-ebook/dp/B008TVM1JU/"&gt;Hamlet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm prone to spend too much  time carefully curating my list of books to read and too little time reading. Hamlet could relate. For bonus points, I intend to watch Kenneth Branagh's production of the play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;William Shakespeare: &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Tempest-Dover-Thrift-Editions-ebook/dp/B00A73FKO6/"&gt;The Tempest&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://oneworld-publications.com/media/preview_files/9781780744261.pdf"&gt;Who else is there?&lt;/a&gt; Incidentally, I'm open to suggestions on how best to read Shakespeare - particular annotated editions, commentaries to read in parallel, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Jane Austen: &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B0083Z3O8Y/"&gt;Emma&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to introduce myself to Jane Austen with a book that isn't Pride and Prejudice simply so that I don't know the ending when I start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Leo Tolstoy: &lt;a href="https://www.audible.com/pd/Anna-Karenina-Audiobook/B01FN88BHC"&gt;Anna Karenina&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opening sentence of this book shows deep insight into both human experience and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anna_Karenina_principle#General_mathematical_backgrounds"&gt;statistics&lt;/a&gt;. The book's been recommended by serveral people who I greatly admire... which is why I've had it on my phone for the last two years. Now to actually read it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Fyodor Dostoyevsky: &lt;a href="https://www.audible.com/pd/Crime-and-Punishment-Audiobook/B002V9ZF3K"&gt;Crime and Punishment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like Anna Karenina, this book has been recommended by two people who I respect tremendously. I bought it years ago, but so far I haven't absorbed it through pure osmosis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Joseph Conrad: &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Lord-Jim-Joseph-Conrad-ebook/dp/B0084753UI"&gt;Lord Jim&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conrad's &lt;em&gt;The Secret Agent&lt;/em&gt; was one of the books that stood out to me when I read it in high school, and I also read &lt;em&gt;Heart of Darkness&lt;/em&gt; a couple years ago. I'm looking forward to another of his novels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Ernest Hemingway: &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B07F42ZNSR/"&gt;For Whom the Bell Tolls&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read two of Hemingway's novels in high school and (as with the Odyssey) I didn't retain much of either of them. I want to revisit Hemingway, and I initially chose &lt;em&gt;For Whom the Bell Tolls&lt;/em&gt; because I'm more interested in the Spanish Civil War than the settings for his other books. Since then, though, I've had the book specifically recommended to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;John Steinbeck: &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B001BC5HXG/"&gt;East of Eden&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know nothing about this book and added it to this list purely based on recommendations. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Vladimir Nabokov: &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B003WUYRB8/"&gt;Lolita&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lolita is a strange book. By all accounts, it's brilliantly written, and three distinct family members recommended I read it. But unlike most of the books on this list, I don't think I've every heard anyone discuss or even reference it. Undoubtedly that's due to the dark subject matter; I expect this to be an emotionally challenging book. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Tim O'Brien: &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Things-They-Carried-Tim-OBrien-ebook/dp/B002TWIVNA"&gt;The Things They Carried&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm interested in this collection of short stories for two reasons. First, the Vietnam War was a defining experience for a generation of Americans, and I don't know much about it. Second, I enjoy well-executed creative writing, and by all accounts this book fits that description.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Philosopy and Criticism&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Adam Smith: &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Theory-Moral-Sentiments-Adam-Smith/dp/1614279985"&gt;The Theory of Moral Sentiments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Capitalism has a bad name among certain members of my generation in part because of the perception that it's divorced from morality. But Adam Smith was a moral philosopher before he was an economist. He writes, "How selfish soever man may be supposed, there are evidently some principles in his nature which interest him in the fortune of others and render their happiness necessary to him though he derives nothing from it except the pleasure of seeing it." &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Herman Wouk: &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Language-God-Talks-Science-Religion-ebook/dp/B00351DSUK/ref=sr_1_2"&gt;The Language God Talks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wouk's &lt;em&gt;The Winds of War&lt;/em&gt; and its sequel &lt;em&gt;War and Rememberance&lt;/em&gt; are two of the most remarkable books I've read. The two novels follow fictional characters navigating the very real events that preceded World War II and characterized the conflict itself. They succeed both as works of history and as novels. I was particularly moved by the depictions of the relationship between father and son, the experience of loss, and, of course, the Holocaust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I dwell on those books because, remarkably, Wouk is still alive and published &lt;em&gt;The Language God Talks&lt;/em&gt; in 2010. The title is drawn from how Richard Feynman described calculus to the author; I'm excited to see what else this slim volume contains about religion and science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Harold Bloom: &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Western-Canon-Harold-Bloom-ebook/dp/B00KK6DGMI/"&gt;The Western Canon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the books on my list are books that Bloom considers part of the Western Canon (although he's since disavowed the list included at the end of this book.) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Alan Bloom: &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B003719GL8/ref=dp-kindle-redirect?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;btkr=1"&gt;The Closing of the American Mind&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've read at least one book (&lt;em&gt;The Coddling of the American Mind&lt;/em&gt;) whose title references Bloom's best seller. It seems only fair to now take a look at the starting point. My suspicion is that the book will probably feel unoriginal to me as a modern reader. If so, that would be precisely backwards; if the book's ideas are conventional, it's because the author successfully shaped convention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Contemporary Nonfiction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Kevin Simler and Robin Hanson: &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B077GZT9Q1/"&gt;The Elephant in the Brain&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not sure this belongs on a "Read before 30" list, but it's a recent book that I'm interested in reading. Anyone who's gone through an undergraduate econ course has been told that much of the value of education comes from signalling. Simler and Hanson take it much further, arguing that almost everything we do is signalling of one type or another. (Why am I writing this post, after all?) It's an interesting premise; I'm curious to see if the whole book feels worth the investment after I've already heard Hanson make the core argument on a podcast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;John Carreyou: &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B078VW3VM7/"&gt;Bad Blood&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The news stories about fraud at Theranos were riveting, and I'm looking forward to reading the whole story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Ben Horowitz: &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B00DQ845EA/"&gt;The Hard Thing About Hard Things&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ben Horowitz is as smart an entrepreneur as you'll find. The episodes of the a16z podcast with him and Marc Andreesen are all fascinating. I'm currently helping my brother build a company, and there's a lot I can learn from reading this book. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Just for Fun&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;James S.A. Corey: &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Tiamats-Wrath-Expanse-Book-8-ebook/dp/B07BVNVWL6"&gt;Tiamat's Wrath (The Expanse Book 8)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the time this comes out in March, I'll be ready to put down the Russian authors and just enjoy the next installment of an excellent Sci-Fi series.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;John le Carre: &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0081KYXQ8/ref=series_dp_rw_ca_1"&gt;Call for the Dead&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the first book in the George Smiley series which includes the better known &lt;em&gt;The Spy Who Came in from the Cold&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Tinker, Tailor, Soldier, Spy&lt;/em&gt;. My sense is that the series is actually though-provoking in addition to being enjoyable, but in either case I want to give it a shot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Terry Pratchett: &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Colour-Magic-Discworld-1/dp/B0000546VE/"&gt;The Colour of Magic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Highly recommended to me, including by an aunt and uncle who named their cat after one of Terry Pratchett's characters. I'm looking forward to finally reading it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That makes 24 books. I'm deliberately leaving myself room to read six more to this list. Perhaps I'll decide to go deeper on one of these authors, or maybe a new non-fiction book will catch my eye. Additionally, I'll continue to read thrillers and the like without adding them to this list.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="books"></category></entry><entry><title>What's wrong with iMessage?</title><link href="http://writing.maxrosett.com/whats-wrong-with-imessage.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-08-06T22:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-08-06T22:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Max Rosett</name></author><id>tag:writing.maxrosett.com,2018-08-06:/whats-wrong-with-imessage.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Apple's iMessage is a big part of iPhone's dominance over Android in the high end market. As others have pointed out, high-end Android phones can largely match the iPhone feature for feature, but the texting experience is a formaldehyde-preserved relic of the flip-phone era.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an iPhone owner, I appreciate …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Apple's iMessage is a big part of iPhone's dominance over Android in the high end market. As others have pointed out, high-end Android phones can largely match the iPhone feature for feature, but the texting experience is a formaldehyde-preserved relic of the flip-phone era.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an iPhone owner, I appreciate the near-seamless ability to switch my messaging between my phone and my Macbook. And no true millennial wants the green text bubble of shame that comes from leaving the Apple ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why has Apple let iMessage become a total disaster? At present, the macOS version and iOS version have at least three visible bugs. Two of these date back at least six months, while the other appeared after I started writing this article. While bugs that affect the iPhone are obviously more important, the ability to use the same messaging service across platforms is a big part of iMessage's appeal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most irritating bug causes messages to appear badly out of order. For whatever reason, iMessage occasionally decides to attach a random timestamp from the future to messages I send. This clumps my messages at the bottom, leaving it looking like I'm having a conversation with myself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Out of Order iMessages" src="http://writing.maxrosett.com/images/out_of_order.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Side note: iMessage prefers to display this bug when I'm discussing private matters, which made getting a screenshot  a real hassle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another annoying bug attaches "not delivered" tags to messages I send from my laptop: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Not delivered iMessages" src="http://writing.maxrosett.com/images/not_delivered.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a while, I found these tags concerning, but they happen so consistently that I just ignore them now. Still, my wife received a lot of duplicate messages from me before I figured out what was going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, if I read a conversation on my desktop, it doesn't clear the unread message notification from my phone. This is the bug that was introduced after I started working on this post. (Admittedly, that was two months ago; I'm an engineer, not a journalist.) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Spurious iMessage Notifications" src="http://writing.maxrosett.com/images/extra_notifications.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the time I took this screenshot, I'd already seen all 16 of these messages on my laptop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of these bugs are backbreaking: I still use iMessage for 95% of my messaging. They also primarily affect users who try to use iMessage seamlessly across different Apple platforms. I have no idea what proportion of iMessage users fall into that category, although by definition we're Apple's highest spending customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, Apple is presumably paying a lot of very smart engineers to work on this product, and I'm genuinely baffled that these bugs were even introduced. This is a company that charges its customers a premium for polished products that just works. How have they let such obvious bugs persist for more than half a year?&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="technology"></category><category term="apple"></category></entry><entry><title>Reflections on the Georgia Tech Online MS in Computer Science</title><link href="http://writing.maxrosett.com/reflections-on-the-georgia-tech-online-ms-in-computer-science.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-07-14T22:47:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-07-21T23:25:21-04:00</updated><author><name>Max Rosett</name></author><id>tag:writing.maxrosett.com,2017-07-14:/reflections-on-the-georgia-tech-online-ms-in-computer-science.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I graduated from Georgia Tech's Online MS in Computer Science &lt;a href="www.omscs.gatech.edu"&gt;(OMSCS)&lt;/a&gt; at the beginning of May. The program is unique in several ways, and enrolling in it was the best professional decision I've made. Specifically, it helped me successfully transition from being a business analyst to being a software engineer …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I graduated from Georgia Tech's Online MS in Computer Science &lt;a href="www.omscs.gatech.edu"&gt;(OMSCS)&lt;/a&gt; at the beginning of May. The program is unique in several ways, and enrolling in it was the best professional decision I've made. Specifically, it helped me successfully transition from being a business analyst to being a software engineer. Now that I've graduated, I'd like to share my thoughts with people who are interested in the OMSCS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The program's biggest strength is the quality of the courses.&lt;/strong&gt; The courses are the most important component of any Master's degree (excluding an MBA) and the OMSCS receives full marks. The courses were rigorous, comprehensive, and challenging. I haven't attended graduate school anywhere else, but I completed several graduate-level courses in math and statistics at Yale and thought that most of my courses were at least as rigorous. &lt;strong&gt;For a student whose primary goal is to learn rather than obtain a credential, the OMSCS is perfect.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hasten to add that I deliberately chose courses that would be challenging; if I'd set out to do the opposite I think I could have made it through the program with only a handful of really challenging classes. That brings me to an unexpected strength of the program: &lt;strong&gt;all of the courses that are offered have numerous high quality reviews&lt;/strong&gt;, currently available on &lt;a href="https://omscentral.com/reviews"&gt;OMS Central.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The site is an unofficial effort created by an OMSCS student (and is the evolution of a previous google spreadsheet.) While most universities have some form of reviews available for students to peruse, many courses either have a small number of reviews or have changed instructors since last being offered. Additionally, students in different departments may have different notions of a "hard" class. By contrast, OMS courses have hundreds of students take them at a time and the lectures at least remain constant from semester to semester, so there are numerous well-calibrated rankings with accurate estimates of the work required each week. Over the last half of the program, I was able to consistently select an interesting set of courses each semester while managing my workload. I realize this seems like a minor point, but it had a real impact on the quality of my experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One slight disappointment is that the OMS didn't add courses as quickly as I hoped. The two results were that I couldn't take some electives (mostly related to machine learning) that looked interesting, and that most of the specializations have limited options to complete their requirements. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Beyond course quality, the next best thing about the OMS is its flexibility.&lt;/strong&gt; When I applied to the program, I was working as a business analyst at a start up and expected to broadly continue along the same path. I was interested in CS but doubted I'd ever work as a developer, so quitting my job and moving across the country to earn a traditional MS was out of the question. I also wasn't interested in a part time program that might have lower-quality courses or a weak reputation among employers. Ultimately, Georgia Tech's strong reputation and the program's low tuition made it appealing, but the flexibility made it possible. Indeed, by the time I finished the program, I had changed jobs twice and moved across the country without having to interrupt my studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one aspect of the OMSCS that's still unclear is the reputation it will have with employers. &lt;strong&gt;The OMSCS should have as good a reputation as Georgia Tech's on-campus program.&lt;/strong&gt; Georgia Tech apparently agrees since they award &lt;em&gt;the exact same degree&lt;/em&gt; to students in both programs. My diploma doesn't say "online"; it's just an MS from a top-ten CS department. Additionally, GT maintains parity between their two MS programs. For instance, the same professor frequently teaches both online and on-campus versions of the same course at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite that, &lt;strong&gt;I see a couple risks that may weaken the program's reputation.&lt;/strong&gt; First, online programs have something of a stigma around them. With time, though, I think that can be overcome, particularly if OMS graduates go on to be successful. Second, the OMS lets in a much larger range of students than other elite programs. In fact, that's the whole point! The high end of that range is fantastic. I was really impressed by some of the classmates, and the work they turned in dramatically outclassed anything I  produced. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the other end of the spectrum, though, some students really struggled with some of the material. If those students go on to receive degrees without mastering core concepts, that may damage the program's reputation in the eyes of employers who hire them. I don't actually believe that it's easier to get through the OMSCS than other MS programs. Instead, many MS programs rely on the admissions office (i.e. GRE scores) to do a lot of filtering for them. Essentially, even they're easy to get &lt;em&gt;through&lt;/em&gt;, they're not easy to get &lt;em&gt;into&lt;/em&gt;. The OMS doesn't have that luxury; its administrators will have to be vigilant about making sure the easiest path through the program is still sufficiently rigorous. If they do that, the program should develop the sterling reputation it deserves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that caveat, I think the OMS is a really fantastic way to learn advanced computer science. The courses are great, and some of the students are phenomenally talented. I think the program will continue to attract remarkable students. Anecdotally, I've been asked about it by people with impressive track records both in education (Yale, Stanford, etc) and employment (Google, Palantir, etc.) I've enthusiastically recommended it to all of them.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="education"></category></entry></feed>